hello welcome back we're here with
Matthew Brown discussing realtime active
inference for adaptive robotic control
so put away the memories that you
haven't had yet and let's talk about
robotics thank you Matt yeah thank you
Daniel yeah this is going to be a bit of
a change in Direction although that was
that was a really great talk I'm looking
forward to reviewing a lot of the talks
from the last um last day um but that
was pretty pretty amazing from China um
so yeah I'm Matt uh great great to be
here um super excited to share updates
about what we're doing um just to give a
little bit of background on myself uh I
I've been working in uh artificial
intelligence for a little over 20 years
um including time in the defense
industry writing AI for video games
things like Halo Bioshock Splinter Cell
those franchises and over the last 10
years been working in more serious AI uh
particularly uh in deep re enforcement
learning and now in active inference uh
notably uh built the first commercially
available deep enforcement learning
platform which was bought by Microsoft
in 2018 is now the autonomous systems
platform there um currently I'm at a a
startup at TH for I began about five
years ago uh thought forge's technology
started as a personal research project
back in 2007 that never really ended
exploring um biologically plausible
alternate approaches to machine learning
uh and in the over the last couple years
have been applying it to Adaptive
real-time control for robotics so that's
what I'm going to be going through today
um just a Qui quick uh brief agenda on
on what what I'll be talking about and
go through a quick uh well not so quick
I'll go through an introduction a lot
about the highle concepts uh then dig
into uh briefly the history of the
project uh and the implementation uh and
then go into some of the more
interesting topics in depth here um
Network self models embodiment
synchronization a lot of the tools that
we're using um to get these um robots to
do interesting things and then um spent
some time talking about uh what we've
been doing with robotics so show some
videos uh perhaps um and just uh explain
a little bit about the direction that
we're going over the next uh couple
years so I'm not going to spend very
long on this slide as is probably
redundant uh you know as the topic toour
I will just briefly emphasize the last
point on the slide here um which is
about um how the free energy principle
provides a unifying framework that
explains how adaptive Behavior Uh
perception and action can emerge from
the drive to maintain a stable internal
state in a constantly changing
environment this is going to be a a
theme throughout the talk so I figured
point that out uh and this one as well I
probably not going to go into too much
but it's worth um noting the last two
points here uh about organisms don't
passively respond to sensory input but
also actively shape their environment
through actions that fulfill their
predictions about their sensory
experience and then also about how
active reference explains how uh
organisms achieve complex self-directed
Behavior by combining sensory processing
processing with active exploration um
this is also uh going to be a common
theme throughout the uh the talk um now
we're going to go a little bit deeper uh
into what we're specifically using for
our robotic uh models uh and the roots
in cybernetics uh um in particular the
relationship between the free energy
principle active inference and
cybernetics which might be obvious to
many people um uh at the Symposium um
cybernetics here being pioneered in the
1940s um also describes self-regulating
systems that adapt to their environments
uh and also kind of uh views agents as
directed systems seeking to main
maintain equilibrium through feedback
loops uh the goal here being to minimize
free energy or surprisal in uh the FP
and active inference uh and you know
active inference kind of operationalizes
this through continuous adjustment of
beliefs and actions um and these
cybernetic ideas are foundational I
believe to how the free energy principle
and active view organisms as systems
that maintain their states within a
predictable range uh and also resists
entropy and disorder by adjusting
internal and external variables um over
time now digging One Step deeper into
the approaches that we're taking here um
I'm going to talk a little bit about um
the cybernetics of Ross Ashby in
particular um uh cybernet Ross aspy he
formalized many key ideas um homeostasis
in particular as the process by which an
organism regulates internal conditions
uh within a narrow optimal range uh in
the face of environmental changes and
disturbance
um he's known for um these are probably
the two biggest things he's known for
the good regulator theorem and the law
of requisite variety uh the good
regulator theorem commonly is quoted is
every good regulator of a system must be
a model of that system um or more
accurately every good regulator must
contain a model of that system um and
with the law of requisite variety the
the common quote is only variety can
destroy variety and you know another way
of thinking about this is a system must
be as complex or more complex than its
envir in order to manage it effectively
or if if one system wants to effectively
uh manage or control another system it
must be at least as expressive and at
least as complex as the system is
controlling um in the active inference
framework an agent maintains homeostasis
by minimizing prediction error
effectively predicting and compensating
for uh environmental fluctuations uh so
this is how Ash's ideas uh really kind
of come into play here as's emphasis on
adaptive regulation through internal
models aligns very closely with active
inferences process of continuously
updating beliefs and taking actions to
minimize prediction error and maintain
uh desired States um Ash's view of
homeostasis as a self-regulating
feedback system is effectively a form of
active inference both involve an agent
using internal models to anticipate in
counteract environmental changes uh
preserving stability and adaptability
through continuous self-correction uh
and Ashby's law of requisite vary here
highlights the you know a lot of the
successes of active uh when active is
successful uh and of maintaining ostasis
here um relying on the system's capacity
to generate a diverse and precise range
of predictions and actions uh without
sufficient variety of responses the
system would fail to adapt leading to a
breakdown in homeostasis and an increase
of prediction eror predictive error
um uh to exemplify these ideas uh Ross
as Ross asby constructed a device known
as the homeostat this was uh back in the
1940s um this was a demonstration of
learning as adaptation as as stability
uh and he believed that behavior is
adaptive it contributes to the
maintenance of these essential variables
uh and there's some various ways of
looking at what he was doing here um
some called it an isomorphism generating
machine uh using feedback to generate
distributed homeostasis via Ultra
stability and and I I'll get more into
that in a little bit um but that's kind
of the approach that we've taken here at
thorge uh and then there's kind of a
long description here from one of his
books about um what the homeostat was
and how to construct it um and all talk
a bit more about how do you construct a
homeostat in a in in a moment here um
here's kind of a quick highlevel
abstract view of home uh sorry Ashby's
original homeostat uh and this is
abstracted away in in a way that uh
reflects kind of modern views of um
mathematical networks here where you you
can define a network as a set of nodes
with connections and weights um and then
he he defined uh Ultra stability as kind
of the the the mechanism that powers the
race of State space B exploration uh
which is used as part of this law of
requisite variety uh and I'll talk uh in
the next slide a bit about that um the
network as a whole creates a dynamic
attractor Set uh as a kind of
self-consistent self-reinforcing uh
model uh and the network can be seen as
kind of a network of reciprocal
constraints um the original the original
homeostat only had four nodes here um
constructed from recycled World War II
bomb parts so this is pre- digital
computer era uh and this uh there a
diagram here kind of conceptually
explaining you know how how it worked um
the original H homeostat itself I think
is is I think at the University right
now but the the the um description of of
how it actually works is uh somewhat
abstract uh I we used uh at ffor we used
a lot of his um technical journals which
were released by his family I Believe In
online in um in the last 15 years or so
um to kind of get more detailed um
information about the properties and how
they're constructed to get a more
accurate uh reconstruction of the
homeostatic um briefly I'm just going to
talk a little bit about Ultra stability
Ultra stability is the property of the
individual node in this network that
enables um the group property of
homeostasis um the ultra stability here
uh is talked about in in Ashby's books
and papers um so I I I don't think it's
necessary to go through a deep deep
analysis of it um but it the ultra
stability mechanism is kind of the the
local the local mechanism within a node
that drives the active process of
self-organization and criticality across
the network uh and it's it's core to the
function of how the homeostat works uh
and it is uh constructed by a double
feedback loop with a low-level feedback
loop that performs like a linear
transformation then a highle feedback
loop um that updates or changes that
linear transformation uh over
time um this is just uh I love I I like
concluding this this this letter uh this
was a letter from um Alan Turing to Ross
Ashby uh way back in when they were kind
of debating on whether or not to go with
analog Computing or or digital Computing
here being uh Ashby being supportive of
the analog Computing Paradigm uh and uh
this letter from tiing is basically
saying that his uh his computer the AC
was more General and more Universal than
Ash's computer because uh you could
Implement Ashby's computer on turing's
machine um and it's just kind of a fun
little piece of History here I I like
including it um just to provide some
context about the time when Ashby was
kind of considering these ideas uh and
why they were kind of lost to time in a
lot of Senses at least within the you
know Computer Science World um and I
also like to bring this up because uh I
think it's the first at at least in my
mind it's the first time um that we
really started conflating uh computation
with cognition here uh and where where
tiing had a universal comp computation
machine uh while Ashby was kind of
envisioning like a a universal uh
adaptation machine you know something
closer to cognition uh and it feels very
similar to a lot of the debate we're
seeing today uh with whether or not deep
learning machines are intelligent or you
know if they can get to AGI uh I think
that a lot of the conflation of
computation and cognition goes all the
way back to the origins of the analog
versus digital debate uh within computer
science um so the next question is how
do you actually build a homeostat uh and
I took turing's advice uh and simulated
we built a simulation of the homeostat
and the reason why simulation is useful
as opposed to like an analytical
solution is because of the chaotic
nature of U of how these systems reach
equilibrium um uh and I used to have a
quote here from ILO P but um essentially
you can't account for a lot of the
chaotic interactions in the systems uh
with loops algebraically uh the
circularities and the the the the cha
the chaos that's necessary for for these
to stabilized require that you do this
iter and that means um building a a a a
simulation that you can kind of step
forward uh
and on the Fly generate the the the uh
chaotic um interactions essentially uh
as opposed to analytically um there's
there's lots of references here with um
you know the three body problem um uh a
mapping of a line onto itself this this
kind of concept of uh uh deterministic
systems when you once you have three
determin deterministic systems
interacting with each other uh you
inevitably get chaotic behavior um that
is kind of leveraged as the
creative uh creative energy that drives
the the um the learning process in this
kind of a system um the techniques that
we use to actually simulate this uh and
this is oops getting ahead of myself
here um it come from a field known as
software radio uh we started out by uh
going through Ashby's technal journals
uh and his writings about how the
homeostat was constructed uh and we
started out by building out uh accurate
analog level digital simulations um and
then from there we kind of abstracted
out all the mechanism specific Machinery
in the analog systems that are not
necessary for the actual function of
ultra stability and homeostasis so kind
of going from this kind of very very
precise analog system to uh kind of
abstracted implementation um of these
four nodes um once functional uh and
this was simple enough to kind of
uh further abstract into more kind of
modern-day Network Theory
implementations where we can kind of
build out very very large networks
similar to how it's done with deep
learning uh that can be connected into
arbitrary Network topologies as opposed
to the original for node Network here uh
and again you just to kind of reiterate
here the network as a whole can be seen
as a self model um each node in this
network is effectively trying to predict
its neighbors as it seeks equilibrium uh
and the the local Ultra stability
process Tunes anodes local connections
and the resulting positive and negative
feedback loops uh that uh that Define it
uh and these overlapping Loops become
self-reinforcing or self-repairing over
time once once you reached kind of um
convergence with these feedback loops uh
the final self-producing set of Loops is
a kind of self- model where each node is
trying to predict all the others and so
once all the nodes kind of reach a
global consensus uh this model this can
be Ed selfconsistent and uh reaches
homeostatic equilibrium um this gener
this can also be seen as kind of like a
generative model uh composed of emergent
self-stabilizing homeostatic feedback
loops uh and these Loops uh are
maintaining this homeostatic equilibrium
in a critical State and this is kind of
an important note for why it is
incredibly sample efficient which is
going to be very important for robotic
applications here um the idea here is
that maintaining this homeostatic
equilibrium at a critical State uh makes
it very sensitive to prediction error
you know the smallest predictive error
uh can trigger a a global structural
change you know um uh so you don't need
to back propagate with a large data set
in order to change the the the model uh
the behavior of the model um a single
misprediction can effectively trigger a
cascading uh set of of redefinitions
where the whole you know the whole
network destabilizes and then Recon
converges on a new attracting set Um
this can also be seen as a form of
synchronization and we'll get into that
uh a little bit later um and the
prediction error reaching zero kind of
marks the establishment of an of a new
adaptive synchronization manifold uh and
the synchronization first starts with
immediate neighbors uh at each node and
then spreads through the entire network
uh as a set of like compound hierarchies
of feedback loops um looking at the time
here
I sometimes I can I could show actually
uh I could switch screens and show
demonstrations of this but maybe I'll
I'll share some of I I'll wait a bit
later to do uh demonstrations of the
original homeostat or kind of larger
homeostat um just so that we're not
switching screens too much um in case
that's useful um all right now we're
getting into some of the more
interesting stuff Le uh less talking
about history uh of cybernetics um so
the the homeostatic Network itself seems
like a lot of work uh in terms of you
know um there's there's a lot going on
there and it's not connected to an
environment it's just learning itself in
coming reaching to convergence without
kind of any um sensory or motor actions
so um we have this model that can adapt
to its internal structure to reach
homeostatic equilibrium through a kind
of self- synchronization process next
step is how do we actually get this to
drive uh Behavior Uh and this took you
know a couple years to kind of work out
the engineering uh conceptually it's
pretty simple um but it will get very
complicated very quickly um the short
version is that the sensors and the
motors uh um basically we Define sensors
of motors uh and they Define how an
agent is embedded into an environment uh
and the network topology separately kind
of defines the Adaptive capacity of the
homeostatic agents model uh the sensor
definitions themselves here um are are
uh kind of defined externally from the
model itself uh they provide a mechanism
to influence the behavior of the system
by providing priors in the form of
preferred sensory States or preferred
environmental States uh and these act as
te teody dnamic priors uh kind of
externally find uh Dynamic set points
for the homeostatic adaptation and these
sensors can be seen as input attracting
sets which can even be modified in real
time or animated in real time to
generate you know different kinds of
behavior from the same model um at
runtime without having to change the
model structure or anything like that uh
the motor definitions then provide you
know kind of critical affordances for
how the agent can modify the environment
to help provide a basis for future
sensory predictions um and the thir
states of the sensors become the
preferred outcomes of the motors through
the this reaching equilibrium State and
the model's Behavior ends up being
biased as desired so this is how we get
it to do useful behavior in a robot for
example um from something that is
seemingly just reaching
equilibrium and I guess one one
important or Salient note here is that
in a real world environment the you know
there it's reaching pure homoy
equilibrium is is actually quite
difficult unless you're um unless you're
in very special circumstances um so to
expand a bit more on on that um the
network diagram here is is kind of an
overly simplified version of our
homeostatic network but meant to kind of
visually explain how to think about
these uh in a particular here um
embodiment of of of these models in kind
of an environment here um coupling it
coupling a model like this to an
environment through sensors and Motors
is kind of a form of embod here meaning
there's a kind of a specific time place
that this model is operating uh and
there is um the there is kind of a
temporal component here where um the the
uh the model's sequence of sensory
Behavior actually is is relevant you the
the um the the inputs to the system are
not independent which is kind of
different than traditional what you
would imagine back propagation based
perceptrons how they function uh and one
thing that's interesting about this uh
and and and it's worth pointing out here
is that there's no forward or backward
no feed forward or feed backward um uh
directions in this kind of network
there's no front or back or top to
bottom um the only thing you can really
kind of uh Direction you can kind of
take from a model like this is distance
from sensors or Motors or or how close
to the environment a particular node is
um otherwise relative location is pretty
much everything you know where as as an
individual node where am I relative to
the rest of the network uh and it's it's
common for people to think of of machine
learning models these days especially if
you're used to to think about deep
learning or traditional perceptron based
back propagation models uh to think of
it as a sequential flow of processing
like uh I take in an input I perceive or
I do planning on that input and then I
generate an action um that's not how
these Network networks uh function uh
instead um everything kind of happens
all the time and everything's
overlapping uh what I mean by that is um
this is not a sandwich model I guess is
is the term time simply advances and
information moves from one node to
another um all in parallel you know so
in in traditional deep learning it's
kind of an atemporal process where
information goes from the inputs to the
outputs instantaneously uh and uh
there's no internal time unless you're
working with recurrent neural networks
and there are ways of adding a temporal
aspect of it but the temporal aspect is
really a fundamental feature of of these
types of notes um what that means is um
the the network itself the the
homeostatic feedback loops come to be
dependent on expected sensory signals u
meaning the the deeper parts of the
network are generating predictive
signals forward to the sensors uh and so
um in order for this to function you the
the deeper parts of the model have to be
actually actively predicting the sensory
inputs that that are coming in um this I
believe also means that it ends up
becoming grounded in the embodied
experience itself meaning the the
homeostatic self-maintenance of this
network is composed of environmental
signals from the Environ from from The
Real World or whatever whatever
embodiment you you you you've put this
model in um and as part of its kind of
predictions and expectations meaning the
the actual sensory experience is what
what is being predicted and so what the
models actually generated is um
generating is is derived originally from
this uh essentially embodied experience
um the expectations and predictions for
the consequences of motor actions are
kind of embedded in the behaviors uh
that are being generated embedded in the
signals sent this uh to the sensors from
deeper in the network at the same time
as these kind of predictive signals are
being sent to the to to the sensory
regions actions are being sent to the
motors um and these actions at any
moment are not based on the latest input
but based on predictions about what the
model believes is going on in the world
world and how best to to kind of satisfy
the sensory inputs or get the the model
into a preferred state or a lower energy
state or or lower surprisal State um
these kind of these motor actions are
accompanied in parallel by sensory
predictions that are all moving kind of
to the to the to the this the uh
the I don't want to say the front of the
network but the the abstraction that
defines the embodiment you know to the
sensors and Motors um in kind of in
parallel um this is this may be familiar
to people who are who are um have read
about perceptual control theory and
predictive processing and very much uh
along those same exact lines in terms of
what's going on here in terms of uh
actively generating predictions to
counteract sensory uh sensory input um
the mo the the motors here end up being
kind of um a critical part of making
those sensory the future sensory
experiences um easier to predict or um
as part of this whole
process another way to look at this this
homeostatic process is through uh
synchronization um the the homeostatic
process can be seen as generating an
Adaptive synchronization manifold
between the agent and the environment um
based around minimization of prediction
error basically uh minimizing the
difference between what I'm predicting
the environment is doing and what the
environment is actually doing this is
kind of a synchronization as prediction
uh process uh where when the two systems
are synchronized they can be thought of
as predicting each other you know um you
know anticipating the other individual
nodes are using uh Ultra stability uh
predict their neighbors and then when at
equilibrium all the nodes are
synchronized through these feedback
loops uh the synchronization between the
noes spreads to whole network
synchronization at this point uh
ultimately uh this synchronization
spreads across this this sensory and
motor abstraction uh between the
environment and and and uh an agent so
you kind of get a um agent environment
synchronization process uh through this
um looking at another way uh these
overreacting feedback loops interact and
synchronize with each other as part of
the homeostatic self-maintenance as
these feedback loops extend from Motors
through an environment back into the
sensors the model gains the ability to
anticipate the consequences of its own
actions uh and the the the capacity to
synchronize internal states with
something in the external World um you
know without direct communication is is
kind of critical to this the
synchronization means that the internal
States become uh uh they they they come
to resemble internal states of the other
system um when and when at this kind of
synchronized homeostatic State it's also
in this kind of critical State sensitive
to local prediction errors um and this
like I mentioned before this is kind of
critical because that allows internally
the model to to completely restructure
itself or redefine how it predicts
Century experience um at the very
slightest misprediction um and uh this
is this is very very critical for sample
efficiency um uh with to contrast this
with you know deep learning models or
deep reinforcement learning models you
need um a a very large amount of data to
kind of change um The Domain the or the
way in which the the models are are
behaving in the world while in these
kind of models it can kind of change at
the uh with the slightest slightest uh
one piece of data can kind of trigger
Global uh Global
restructuring um so one interesting
aspect here is that in order to maintain
a synchronization manifold the network
must be able to converge to equilibrium
faster than the environment can
destabilize it and so this kind of goes
back to um as's theory of uh the good
regulator theorem or the law of
requisite variety where the model has to
be ex more complex than the environment
is trying to to control um and has to be
at least as expressive as the as the as
the uh the environment is in terms of
coming up with Solutions um and you know
uh yeah actually I was going to go a bit
more into synchronization uh and how
once once the network is synchronized
with an environment um once two elements
internal to those systems are
synchronized they can kind of coordinate
without direct communication and this is
kind of important to the whole process
as so that the sensor and motors abstra
don't have to be the direct link between
uh an aspect of the model and an aspect
of the environment once synchronized
those two pieces can coordinate in terms
of their behaviors will be coordinated
without direct communication between the
two um so now on to some more fun stuff
um the killer application of all this is
robotics uh other early Avenues we
looked into is uh for example applying
this for anomaly detection um where you
can of use the network as a a
thermometer for surprisal um the other
way you can kind of use this applied to
like modern deep learning is for like a
model dri drift detection where you can
kind of uh use the model to um detect
when a deep Learning System is being
used on a uh if if the input stream to a
deep Learning System is being is
diverging from the model uh domain so
like if the sorry the the trading domain
so if the data set you used to train it
on is starting to differ from how it's
actually being used uh this could kind
of uh be useful for that um but really I
feel like robotics is really the killer
application for this especially when you
consider the embodied nature of it um
you know this the embodiment is kind of
a requirement for how this model Works
in terms of having to be embedded in an
environment with uh this could be a
virtual environment as well but it has
to have some sort of uh sensory motor
coupling um to something external to
itself um also the the ability to kind
of understand context over time and
understand that um even for a sensory
input that is the same as some other uh
uh a sensory input at another time the
the the the things that have happened
previous to it are relevant you know um
and so building up this context
awareness uh through interaction with
environment is kind of critical to how
our models work um but also very
important for for robotics uh and then
real-time adaptation um of the model
being able to update the model in real
time as actions are being performed um
is kind of a really useful technique in
robotics in order to enable many uh
dexterity uh and and adaptation in the
moment um that is missing from a lot of
robotic applications here uh and
specific to deep reinforcement learning
and deep learning ways of doing robotic
control there's this uh field known as
Sim toore and so uh Sim toore problems
come from uh deep reinforcement learning
is is where they're commonly referred to
but it's where the models are sensitive
to simulation Fidelity uh the idea being
you've trained a model in some in
simulation um and how the model behaves
is very sensitive to the specifics of
the the physics in that simulation or
you know the actual Fidelity of that s
uh that simulation and so moving to the
real world often shifts the input domain
uh and deep reinforcement learning and
deep learning models are not usually
robust for these kinds of changes uh
unless you you drastically increase the
amount of data through domain
randomization uh which causes other
problems such as the cursive
dimensionality there's all sorts of
solutions to the Sy the real problem for
us we sidestep all this by leveraging
real-time learning and adaptation so um
when the model is in presented with
something new or unusual in the moment
we we don't we don't separate the the
training phase from the deploy you know
the the inference phase it it as it's
inferring it's doing the updating and
the learning um and this this kind of
solves a lot of the centore problems um
as the model is able to adapt to
whatever differences uh happen in the
real world that were not represented in
simulation um so this is a lot of re uh
a longwinded explanation of why we went
after robotics for applying these these
kinds of models um to get into more kind
of robotic side of things in terms of
technical detail in terms of how we're
actually implementing this um for a lot
of our interoperability between a lot of
different robots um the model itself
doesn't really care what kind of robot
you apply this to uh so you get a lot of
Hardware agnosticism where you can take
a model built for one arm uh the robot
arm and apply it to another robot arm
for example uh and the model will adapt
to any kind of kinematic differences
between the two that kind of thing um
this is a diagram of how we fit into
Ross Ross is the Robot Operating System
and it's it's the it's the open- source
uh
academic uh software framework that is
used uh across that supports a lot of
robots it's not used in a lot of
industrial settings um but it's
incredibly flexible in its ability to
experiment and try new things and so
we've kind of used this as our kind of
beach head uh robotic stack
implementation um these uh homeostatic
models are particularly small uh so they
only operate like the uh typically about
30k of memory so uh they they can
operate on edge devices you know no TPU
needed uh no Cloud needed uh in fact you
you want to run it as close to the robot
as possible to minimize latency in the
control um phase uh and just runs in in
a single CPU um because of our our
implementation of ultra stability and
this homeostatic networks are are quite
efficient uh model update times our sub
millisecond so this enables us to um
update the model and update the the uh
that synchronization manifold um as a
task is being performed you know uh
We've clocked the networks being able to
run up to 80 khz um but for most robotic
control algorithms 500 htz or th000 or 1
khz is typically fantastic and most
robots don't support anything above that
um and there's you know there's Al also
some other interesting aspects to the mo
the the the technical side of things
where the models are small enough we're
talking 30k here where um analytical
explainability is possible where we can
take a look at a robotics action and
actually analyze the homeostatic Network
to figure out um which sensory inputs or
which you know which motor out uh which
sensory inputs led to a particular
decision um and because the models are
small enough we can kind of use
different kinds of network analysis
approaches uh to figure that out uh on
the more technical detail side in case
it's useful the our models are built in
C++ and we have a python wrapper so that
gives us a lot of integration to
capabilities to lots of different robots
um which is is is useful and
fun um so just going to go through some
of the applications that we've done in
the past uh and I could I could bring up
a demonstration and and do it live uh
this this was a uh a use case we did uh
for a company for uh adaptive inspection
so they had a use case where uh they
have autonomous vehicles going through
um going through a field and they needed
a robotic arm to kind of uh compensate
for um movement or unexpected you know
orientations and and configurations of
of the of the uh autonomous vehicle base
um without knowing ahead of time what it
was going to encounter uh and so yeah
this was kind of a a fun interesting uh
pretty simplistic model that we built
for them uh and you can see kind of a
fun video here of it in our lab kind of
tracking this this QR code um and uh
going one step further in terms of uh of
difficulty this was another use case um
from a different customer um they had a
challenge of um they they were seeing an
injury with um turning high pressure gas
valves and uh they wanted to automate
this with robots the problem was that
they never have a good accounting for
what kind of valve or what kind of uh
you know thing that needs to be turned
what it was going to look like what the
shape of it was going to be if it was
going to be rusty and difficult to turn
or if it was going to be covered in oil
and slippery or if the edges were going
to be worn off um so they needed
something that can adapt to this high
level of variability um uh in real time
um without access to the internet
because this was on you know remote
locations uh and so we built this model
for them um and you this is just kind of
a fun little video of it um we've turned
this into an interactive demo that we've
brought to conferences which is um kind
of fun here this is uh this is just
recorded on a cell phone you can tell it
was it's it's real based on the
production qualities um but this was
that that that valve turning model that
we we created before um except we've
just kind of adapted it here so that we
can you know show off people torturing
it um in real time live as it tries to
kind of turn these bolts of various
shapes uh and sizes um you know some
interesting things to note here the
original model that we built for this um
only took about uh 15 seconds to train
three examples essentially uh and it was
only it was only trained on a single um
bolt shape here uh the square in fact uh
and then what we do is we kind of show
how it can kind of generalize to all the
these other different cases here in real
time without having seen any of these
examples before uh and at the beginning
of the video there you can kind of see
on the screen um uh our our internal
it's our internal debugger but it's a
fun visualization because you can see
the the homeostatic Network um learning
in real time as you kind of move this um
this uh panel of bolts around um I'm
just stalling a little bit there we go
so you can see those little those little
squiggly lines there on on the on the
screen um that's the that's kind of a
view into the 30 of the nodes of the
network kind of um updating in real time
as we're as we're kind of having it turn
these knobs
here um getting into the less
interesting stuff but just to kind of
show uh where we are as as a technology
um this is a platform we're building uh
currently this is used internally um to
develop new models uh and we have um
some some interesting tools here that
allow you to um effectively search
ranges of topologies to to experiment
with different kinds of uh Network
topologies for particular task um and
then see what the performance looks like
in in simulation and kind of iterate on
this uh eventually you'll also be able
to uh connect your robot to the platform
and download the model directly um so
that you can go straight from um
designing uh a goal specification we
call a goal specification but really
what is what you're doing is you're
defining those T Dynamic priors in the
sensor uh sensor definitions as part of
that embodiment uh definition uh and
then you go and you evaluate what
topology is optimal for the you for that
for that definition and then you can
deploy this directly onto your robot uh
in the real world and try it out
um next steps or the direction that
we're heading um is is kind of
interesting um right now a lot of the
models that we're building are very kind
of small and uh task specific um but
we're building them in a way that is
recomposed of building one model that
does a task like turning the valves this
that that task is actually composed of
three smaller models and the here is
we're building up a library of
recomposed submodels uh so that we can
kind of recompose them in uh in in
simple ways to go after new tasks uh so
the idea here is we can take um right
now we only have a handful of submodels
but over the next year or two're
building out this larger library of
submodels that can be recomposed to go
after a much wider variety of tasks uh
and um so this this diagram here is is
meant to show how we're kind of looking
at um building up this framework of Rec
composable models uh eventually that
platform you saw this one here um
eventually will'll probably open this up
for the public uh to go and compose
their own models from these recomposing
submodels uh and um then we can even
string together you know many models
together and and um have a framework for
deciding when to use which model um
because they're only about 30k of memory
uh you can really kind of load up uh a
robot with you know let's say a thousand
models for example uh and you can kind
of get a lot of generality just from um
a collection of sub problems being
solved individually in in a robust
manner um so I went through this talk
pretty quickly I fig I'll just end with
some current work that we're looking at
uh right now we're working on a um this
is just kind of an early look in
simulation of of an insertion task um
we're working on uh what's interesting
about this is that we can't use vision
for a lot of this because once the
insertion process happens um the the arm
kind of includes the view of it so we're
incorporating uh four sensors uh so that
we can kind of Wiggle you know tight
fitting pieces into a um a housing for
example uh and you really kind of need
to build in um uh this kind of nuanced
uh feeling of you know wiggling
something into place this comes very
naturally to humans you know um in terms
of like filling your way through a
problem uh and so we're we're kind of um
working on building out the submodels
needed here for high frequency Force
torque sensors for wiggling uh things
into place um to to kind of broaden the
amount kind applications that we can we
can start attacking with this approach
um so that's that's kind of uh some
current work that we're working on um I
kind of blazed through that really
quickly I could show some live
simulation demos but um maybe questions
maybe it makes sense to just move on to
questions thanks Matt that was awesome
I'll ask some of the questions in the
chat maybe we'll we'll still have time
to to see the demo but that was that was
really
exciting um okay I'll start with black
cat who wrote very cool how would you
say
interoperability challenges change from
software to
Hardware that that's inter a question
there's different ways to think about it
um moving to software things I think get
a lot easier um as Hardware is always
hard uh and always timec consuming um
for us we're using Ross to get a lot of
interoperability between different kinds
of robots but Ross is nonoptimal for for
a lot of lot of situations and so there
is going to be some sort of low-level
drivers that we we'll have to to write
that are kind of going to be Hardware
specific but for the most part most
robot uh uh manufacturers or oems they
have an interface that is that provides
some sort of joint control so the models
right now are uh generating effort-based
controls uh that we then convert into
you know positional based controls
because that's the most common most
robots do not support effort-based
controls um but pretty much all robotic
arms in particular have some sort of
joint space control uh interface so we
can
basically all we need is kind of a
driver to translate the output of the
model into uh joint Space controls for
that particular robot um the other thing
that's kind of interesting and you don't
get this with deep enforcement learning
is that um we don't actually
specifically tell the model um what each
motor output does we we we do have we do
specify how many motor outputs there are
from the model um uh although I guess we
could overestimate we can give it more
more actions larger action space than it
actually has and will just kind of learn
to ignore or it will just there will
become no correlations between the
unused actions and the sensory space so
it ends up being unnecessary um but
because we don't actually specify what
each motor action is doing um it learns
that uh meaning like it it will in the
first couple uh of milliseconds of
interacting uh with the it considers the
robot part of the environment let me put
it that way so in the first couple
milliseconds of of controlling this
robot it will build up those
correlations of oh if I apply a positive
effort on this joint it moves me away
from my target or if I move apply a
negative it gets me closer to it kind of
figures out those correlations and as
you know as a process of it learning how
to get to equilibrium if that makes
sense um and as a result of that we get
a lot of um Hardware agnosticism so with
that that valve turning model for
example it was originally built for a
different robot it was originally built
for a he heavy six degree of Freedom arm
um the customer ended up deploying it on
actually a different heavy robot with
with an additional actuator um and the
model can kind of you know we basically
added an output to it um but the model
can kind of adapt to that situation
there um for those videos you just saw
and and at that conference we then took
that same model and deployed it on a
different manufacture uh with a six
degree Freedom arm uh and it kind of
just figured out you know what it needs
to do differently uh that robot is
really nice because it fits in a
suitcase so it's really great to travel
with so from from the uh moving to
software and especially moving to this
particular way of looking at the
interface um it buys you a lot of
interruptibility bonuses that you don't
get with other approaches um but there
is still you're still dependent on the
hardware orem's driver level interfaces
um but generally those are all the same
uh with they the interfaces are all the
same even if spinning up the robot might
have different
mechanisms awesome Six Degrees of
ACM I'm I'm going to Cluster two
questions together so erun asked how
much of this is or will be open source
and Alexander Robbia asked wonderful
talk Matt I'm a huge fan of the
homeostat as you know have you given
thought to perhaps translating the
homeostat to its core set of equations
dynamics and contributing them to open-
Source projects like NGC learn so others
can appreciate its
value oh great question um
and great great I'm glad to hear Alex is
on the call um these are both great
questions
um I I'm always torn in terms of like
what to open source and what not to open
source um I think eventually we are
going to open source a lot of this um
right now the intellectual property of
of this approach
is one of the things that is most
valuable about our current business so
from a business perspective in the short
term we're probably not going to open
source a lot of this we are expecting to
open up our platform to to a wider
audience um over over time
um I and actually I should follow up
with Alex I we have actually kind of
distilled down um our implementation of
the homeostat at least you know there's
a lot of inter interpretations I want to
say there have been five or six
implementations of the homeostat over
the last 80 years or so uh and they're
all different which is kind of
interesting uh there's a lot of room for
interpretation but at least our
implementation of it we have kind of
distilled down to a relatively simple
set of equations and they they they are
very very similar to kind of the the
um equations using the perceptron with a
couple of very subtle changes the the
the subtle changes here having drastic
effects one one is that we've added
state to the to the to the node um which
really changes how how you think about
these things as perceptrons are
generally stateless and so the adding of
the state there kind of adds that
temporal notion so even though it's a
subtle change it has drastic
implications for how how the actual
model Works um but uh and actually I
might I was trying to see if I have it
as an extra slide here in in the top
um I might follow up with Alex and and
share uh share those the equations I'm
I'm less concerned about um sharing kind
of you know the approach and and the and
the uh the uh equations for for our
definition of the hom stat just because
these are very very difficult to
implement uh and I would kind of Welcome
more ideas and activity in the space and
I need to take a closer look at ngtc
learn uh I've I've been I keep seeing uh
uh things being added to NGC learn uh
and it's it's relatively new package but
there's a ton in there uh and I really
kind of need to take a look at what's in
there um and if we do open source it
does make sense to maybe integrate that
as potentially an option in NGC learn um
a lot of it depends on whether or not
the interface is compatible with what
we're doing and I I say that not because
as a as a limitation of NGC learn but
more of as a limitation of how people
think about machine learning models as
kind of um most most Frameworks that are
built around deep learning um their
interfaces kind of assume uh a temporal
you know uh Behavior where each input is
kind of independent uh each input output
relationship is independent of the
others um but I think it's just it's a
matter of me just taking a look at NGC
learn and how it how it's structured and
how to actually interface with it but I
think if we do eventually open source um
the code um that might be the the best
Avenue to do it just because that way it
would be alongside a lot of this other
great ideas for nonb back propagation
based machine learning thank you Matt
and and also really appreciate like
sharing that Insight it isn't a uh open
and shut and just because we can open
source something doesn't mean we could
or could in that way or should tomorrow
or whatever happens to be so so hearing
your your well-worn experience about all
of this is is really insightful um okay
another question from Alex he wrote how
do you go about designing the structure
of your homeostat net is it a random
graph that you instantiate or some other
graph type type does it depend on the
robotic control
problem that is a great question and
just right off the St off the start I
I'll mention that it's unsolved like
it's something that we're still working
on um in terms of how we do it now um so
longer term I would love to start with
like a random graph and then have some
sort of um metric for evaluating what
graph is better than another graph for
particular use case and and we're
probably pretty close to there and then
we could have some sort of mutation
function and that that way you could
kind of evolve what the right to is for
a particular graph I think that actually
has a lot of promise and I'd really love
to get into that kind of stuff right now
um what we're doing is a half step in
that direction um we have found that the
topology has a big impact on how good
the model is at performing particular
task meaning you can take a random model
and then try to have it turn vs for
example um but often it'll do a pretty
poor job or um it'll be slow or it'll be
a little wobbly um and and so really
kind of fine-tuning what the topology is
for a particular task is is critical if
you actually want a really effective
robotic control model uh and so way that
we've been solving this is um for for
specifically robotic control we've come
up with a a way of parameterizing the
topology um and this kind of constrains
the search process for what is finding
the right topology and then what we do
is in that platform you saw in this
platform the primary thing that this
platform is doing is providing an
interface to do that topology search so
in the back end here uh when you
actually are trying to find what is the
optimal topology for a particular use
case what's actually going on is that
it's using that um that kind of
parameterized search space and doing
doing a big search uh and so we're
actually leveraging some Cloud compute
here for this not a ton uh it's not
particularly expensive the training
process only takes about 15 seconds for
per model so um so what we're we're
using any scale which is built on an
open source technology called Ray uh
which is uh really good at spinning up
let's say of CPUs at once uh and so the
idea here is we can go and spin up uh
20,000 different topologies uh and then
evaluate of those 20,000 which one is
optimal for a particular use case and
this process takes about five minutes uh
and so uh we're trying to get that as as
short as possible so that this is kind
of a compilation time interaction as
opposed to you know training the model
for a day and then coming back and
seeing how it performs you can go and
like explore 20,000 different topologies
and figure out which one is optimal for
your particular use case so that's our
current approach which is kind of like a
brute Force approach um but longer term
I would love to get to that evolutionary
uh approach where we kind of start with
a random model maybe we can estimate
what a good starting size is or maybe we
have some sort of um uh some you know uh
heuristic for deciding whether or not to
strength the model or or grow the model
um but you know the to contrast it with
deep learning um this is one of the
downsides of the approach is that the
topology itself is uh is very critical
for good good performance as opposed
with deep learning you can often just go
with a larger model and just give it
more data and you can kind of get the
same performance as a smaller model um I
think this makes sense uh from a
biologic biological standpoint in the
sense that our our brains are not just
randomly connected they are evolved over
time you know uh and you can imagine how
some brains might perform better at
certain tasks than other brains um and
so I think this this topology dependent
behavior is not necessarily
um problematic or or wrong uh this just
something we have to deal with awesome
I'll read a comment from Scott David
this is as most emissions from Scott's
language model it's not necessarily a
question so if you have a response scope
for it and then I do have a question
that that also connects with Ian and
little interception so Scott
wrote it is interesting to consider the
hardware software question of
application of active inference in light
of the historical counter of Claude
Shannon with Von noyman when Shannon was
encouraged to apply the second law of
Thermodynamics to his quantitative
theory of information thermodynamics at
the edge of tangible and intangible
information domains the ubiquity of the
expression of the second law results in
it being a foundational Vector for
interoperability including across
tangible hard and intangible soft
domains there's a lot there I might I
might need to take a look at that in
text form and and come up with a
coherent response um textually um but
there's a lot there um there's there are
a lot of information you know Shannon
level information constraints in the
you're right in at the hardware level
especially when you're talking about um
update rates you know for example um the
model the model as a part of its
embodiment has a temporal aspect to it
too in terms of um the frequency of
updates of the model has to be
consistent like you can't update it you
know 100 times per second you know for
one second and then a million times per
second for the next second so there is
um there are kind of interesting
information Theory do you know problems
here with you know nyis theorem like uh
as the sensory inputs are coming in um
are are you getting sensory inputs at a
high enough frequency to
actually makes make interesting
inferences about them or is on the
robotic side there are absolutely uh
control constraints you know if you're
only able to take an action once per
second there's you're very limited in
terms of what you can do with a robot as
opposed to if you can take an action
every 500 every you know 2 milliseconds
uh there's a lot more Nuance uh in in
the feedback process that of in the
control so there's absolutely some
information theoretic stuff um on on
that interface in that embodiment you
know definition um for the most part I
haven't I I don't want to say we've done
anything particularly Innovative on that
side it's just these are all things that
you kind of have to understand as part
of like the constraints of of the
implementation um but uh definitely send
me the text for that uh that question
and I'll try to come up with a more
coherent and thorough response um there
was a lot in there cool and the
historical part was was was epic um okay
here's a a question so Ian not sure
which parts you listen to from prior
maybe Matt give a first pass but I was
really interested when you mentioned the
difference between the position sensors
and the effort
sensors so how does that play out in
robotics and then like Ian to the
interception
an introspection
angle in what ways do does our postural
adjustment relate to
positional inference and effort
inference that's a fun question um
unfortunately I haven't feeling my
answer is going to be not part not too
interesting um in terms of we're not
doing anything particularly Innovative
here either um the the outputs of the
model are almost unitless uh in the
sense that they'll they'll kind of adapt
to their embodiment in terms of like so
we've kind of been interpreting them as
efforts or like you can think of this as
like torque controls um the for robotics
this is problematic though because first
of all like I want to say 90% of robots
or 90 not five% of robots don't support
torque based controls that requires
there there are just a few robots out
there that require that and for the most
part they're they're confined to
research applications um the reason but
you know the reason why they exist and
the reason why there's a lot of interest
in it especially with deep reinforcement
learning is is there's if you can go to
effort-based controls or Torque based
control contrs directly to the robot
there's a lot of nuanced Behavior you
can get you can get really kind of uh
compliant Behavior where the robot's
applying just enough Force to perform a
Tas that way if you bump into it it's
it's not going to hurt anything and
it'll it'll be compliant and you can
kind of get a lot of nuanced Behavior
with torque base controls but the
reality is that 95% of robots don't
support that they just support either
velocity controls or or you know
positional controls of some kind uh and
so to to solve that you know we're we
basically convert the effort output of
the model into a relative positional
change and then we basically integrate
that relative positional change over
time to get an absolute positional
control um so not particularly
interesting on that side but uh it is
kind of a technical note that's that's a
bit challenging on the robotic side of
things um it does I you know I hadn't
really thought about it enough from an
active inference perspective in terms of
like what does that mean for um you know
the the attracting set that you're
you're you're bringing and a lot of it
is because it's it's somewhat
disconnected from the sensory inputs
like um you know you know what I mean
like the positional controls end up
impacting the environment in some way
and then you know connecting the dots
kind of indirectly that affects your
sensory inputs um but they're the it's
not like a direct it it's not like the
the positional versus effort outputs of
the robot are directly changing how our
sensory experience happens it's more
that like it might change the the
effectiveness of or the capabilities of
your robot uh to it to to alter the
environment if that makes sense um but
maybe I need to think a bit more about
that because that is kind of an
interesting aspect that I I hadn't
really considered
enough how does that play out in the
body Ian oh yeah that's really
interesting I've joined this
conversation late but thanks for
including me Daniel um so yeah I was
kind of listening to that with interest
and thinking
of you know how we as a human something
simple like the the concept of being
hungry hungry and angry at the same time
and how that affects our behavior when
you've got complete competing kind of um
uh interests or physiological variables
that you're trying to deal with and then
thinking about okay a robot something
simple to start off with like maybe a um
one of these robotic lawnmowers that
needs to go back to its docking station
to charge up for
fuel um so it you know it needs to end
the task it's doing and move back to its
docking station and charge up but as
robots get more sophisticated and
they're trying to please humans more but
there will be some kind of you know I
don't know some limit to its um
capabilities its internal processing or
power that's and maybe at some point it
will say it's you know absolutely have
to weigh up all of these and come to
some computation about what it needs to
do next to satisfy its own and this
honestly I think ties into some of the
stuff that Alex has been talking to
about with like moral competition as
well um if I'm GNA be honest the robot
control bottles were making are far less
complex than an actual biological entity
like a human um but you're absolutely
right because you're going to have all
sorts of here right now we're kind of
having these kind of first layer sensory
inputs kind of defining the tele damic
PRI but you can imagine like a hierarchy
where you have like other models that
are feeding outputs that feed into your
motor controls because these motor
controls are are kind of the the end
point for for modifying the environment
but you can imagine why you would be
reaching for a a cup of water is is
driven by some other network that's
saying oh you're thirsty um and uh and
so we just you know I'm just not nearly
there in of complexity yet but I think
you're right eventually we will be
especially if you want to have robots
that are fully self self-sufficient
fully autonomous know when they need to
repair themselves and then going out and
Performing those repairs uh whatever
that might be maybe it's charging um I
think you're absolutely right I think
that's the future uh longer term I love
it thank you Matt great times till next
time yeah likewise
bye e